Hello, everyone, and
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine,
and Marco, today we're
talking about a very
important part of daily life.
That's right, today
we're going to take a look
at a lesson about
technology and something
that has become so
popular and part of our
everyday lives that it's necessary
for us to acknowledge it in English.
That's right, so we're talking about cellular
phones, but not just cellular phones.
Everything you can do and that many
people often do on their cellular phones.
That's right, so
before we get into that,
let's listen to the
dialogue, try to understand
what it's all about, and
we'll be back in a bit.
Why didn't you text me last night?
What?
I sent you three or four messages.
I didn't get any of them.
I was waiting for you
to text me the address
of where the party wasn't
and never got your message.
Why didn't you just call?
I hate sending SMS messages.
Well, because I didn't have any credit
on my phone, I used it all up this month.
I thought you had an unlimited SMS plan.
I do, but if I don't
have any credit on my
phone, it won't let me
call or send messages.
No one knew you didn't get my texts.
All right, we're back, so now let's
take a look at language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
First up on language takeaway, we have the
verb that is the focus of today's dialogue.
Do text.
That's right.
So this is a verb in this
case to text, text me.
Why didn't you text me?
Now, remember that text means
other things in other situations.
Right.
Here, it's a verb.
It's a very new word as a verb from the
last maybe 15 years or so with cell phones.
So that's actually what it means is
to send a text message via cell phone.
So you send a message.
That's right.
So you actually write the message, right?
It's not a call.
When I call you, I talk to you.
When you text someone, you
actually write a message, it's very
short, and then you send it,
and the other person can read it.
Right.
So instead of saying, why didn't
you send me a text message last night?
We just say, why didn't you text me?
All right.
Now, another word that we often hear about
texts is the noun messages or message.
So I sent you three or four messages.
That's right.
So when we're talking about texting someone,
what we're doing is sending a message.
A text message.
That's right.
Because we can send a voice message.
So voice is me talking.
Hi, Marko.
It's Catherine.
How are you doing?
Right.
But a text message is actually words.
I write them out.
That's right.
So, but then we could actually
use the verb form as well.
So we can say to
text, or we can say to
message, why didn't you
message me last night?
That's right.
So this is more slang
to message someone
because text is very
common and everyone uses it.
But normally young
people say, hey, why
didn't you message me or aren't
you ever going to message me?
Right.
Or stop messaging in class.
That's right.
These are verbs to text and to message.
If we see a down
towards the middle of the
dialogue, we see that the person
hates sending SMS messages.
So it's kind of, you
know, explaining already
what's been said because
you have SMS messages
and this abbreviation stands for short
message service, short S message M service S.
So short message service, but most
people around the world say SMS.
Right.
So send me an SMS or
send me an SMS message,
which again, like, like
we see in the dialogue,
it's kind of contradictory
because we're
already saying short
message service message.
Yeah, but most people
don't know what SMS means.
So they just say, hey, send me an SMS
message or send me a text message.
Right.
I didn't get your SMS.
That's right.
Now lastly, we didn't get the SMS because
we didn't have any credit on the phone.
All right, now credit is
an important word here.
It's a noun.
It's a thing we have credit
or we don't have credit.
And it's important to remember
that credit stands for money.
All right.
So maybe I buy $10 of
credit for my cell phone.
And that means I can
send many, many messages.
But when I have zero credit,
I can't send any messages.
That's right.
Well, this is important
because usually in
many places, you have
to have this amount of
money in your phone in order to
be able to talk and send messages.
So this money that
you have is called credit.
So you can say, I don't
have any credit on my phone.
That's right.
And it's basically a way of having
money without having real money.
You actually buy credit
from your cell phone
provider, like AT&T, or if
you have China Telecom.
That's who you buy credit from.
That's right.
Very good.
Let's listen to the dialogue again
and we'll be back with fluency builder.
Why didn't you text me last night?
What?
I sent you three or four messages.
I didn't get any of them.
I was waiting for you
to text me the address
of where the party wasn't
and never got your message.
Why didn't you just call?
I hate sending SMS messages.
Well, because I didn't have
any credit on my phone.
I used it all up this month.
I thought you had an unlimited SMS plan.
I do, but if I don't
have any credit in my
phone, it won't let me
call or send messages.
No wonder you didn't get my texts.
All right.
We've prepared three phrases for you.
Let's start with those
now in fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
So we're still talking about credit here.
Now, when you have credit, you can use it.
But if you use all of it,
we say you use it all up.
Right, we used it up to use something up.
So here, what does the up do?
Because we can use something
like I'm using my toothbrush, right?
But to use up is different, right?
It means that you finished
it, you, it no longer exists.
So it's, it's completed.
Right.
I had credit.
I used it up.
That means it is gone.
Right.
Exactly.
So for example, maybe
paint your painting a
room and you just, you used
up all the white paint, right?
So you used all the paint,
you have no more paint.
It's gone.
So it's all used up.
It's a very important phrase
to remember it's used up.
That's right.
Now going back to
SMS and messages, the
question came up and said, I
thought you had an unlimited SMS plan.
All right.
So an unlimited SMS plan.
We know what SMS
means, but first of all,
let's talk about a plan
because when we talk
about cell phones, it's important to
remember that some people buy credit.
That's how they get service.
But some people buy plans.
Right.
This is very popular,
by the way, in America.
This is how most phones are.
Right.
What is a plan?
So basically it's just
like any other service,
like maybe internet,
you, you pay a monthly
fee and you get a certain
amount of this service.
So maybe you pay $50
and you get a hundred
minutes to use on your cell phone
and unlimited amount of SMS.
All right.
Basically, my cell
phone provider, AT&T or
telecom, they will say,
for this price, you get
this much time, this many
messages each month.
Right.
And you have to keep paying it.
Normally it's one year or two
years that you have to commit.
You can't say, nah, I
don't want this anymore.
Right.
Exactly.
But the important thing here is that
the person bought an unlimited SMS plan.
So this keyword, their
unlimited means it has no limit.
It means you can use
it as much as you want.
So unlimited, no limits, that means
there's, you can do it as much as you want.
Right.
You can have unlimited calls,
you get an unlimited SMS.
You can have unlimited data, for example.
Right.
Exactly.
Very good.
And we ended with
saying, well, no wonder you
didn't get my text, well,
because he didn't have credit.
I wonder, you didn't get it.
I know wonder is a
great and very important
phrase and it's something we say when we
finally understand why something happened.
Right.
We realize what happened.
So Marco, gosh, why didn't
you respond to my calls?
Well, I didn't have any credit.
No wonder.
That means, oh, now I understand.
Exactly.
The great phrase to start off your sentence
by explaining or letting the other person
know that you finally
understand why this happened
or you understand what
would the situation was.
All right.
So let's take a listen to
the dialogue one last time.
Why didn't you text me last night?
What?
I sent you three or four messages.
I didn't get any of them.
I was waiting for you
to text me the address
of where the party was and
I never got your message.
Why didn't you just call?
I hate sending SMS messages.
Well, because I didn't have
any credit on my phone.
I used it all up this month.
I thought you had an unlimited SMS plan.
I do.
But if I don't have any credit on my phone,
it won't let me call or send messages.
No wonder you didn't get my texts.
All right.
We're back.
So talking about messages and everything
are, do you send a lot of messages?
Because I know some people
send like 100 messages a day.
Well, that usually teenagers.
Yeah.
I don't send 100 messages a day.
I mostly use messages.
I don't call people very often.
I find that messages
are easier and cheaper.
Right.
But I can't imagine sending a thousand
messages a day or a hundred messages a day.
Your thumbs would get so tired.
Well, I remember,
well, this is back in the
day when you had the
little Nokia phones and
you didn't have the touch
screens and all this stuff.
I did have some friends
who were very, very
agile with with, you know,
sending these messages
and some did send
like, I don't know, a
hundred, 200 messages
a day because it was, it
was that new way of
communicating with people.
Yeah.
It's very exciting.
And I will also mention, and this is
something that my parents complain about.
There is something in
America and I'm sure in
England as well called
text talk or text speak.
And so because
messages are short, people
have started to change the
way they spell or write words.
Right.
So instead of saying, F-O-R, this is for
you, they write, this is number for you.
Right, exactly.
And it's so funny because
you see these normal
words, but written
in a strange new way.
Yeah.
And people who are
older, I think my parents
age, and I do too, to some extent, really
don't like it because it's so different.
Right.
It's especially very
popular with the younger
generation because it translates
now to all sorts of messaging.
So not, you know,
before, as you say, it was
because of the limitations, the amount
of characters you could send in a message.
But now it's just become something that
people have gotten in the habit of doing.
So, for example, instead of
writing, skate, you know, like
skateboard, they would write S-K,
and then the number eight, so skate.
So skate.
Skate.
It's so strange.
And I know it actually happens
in other languages as well.
Yeah, a lot.
Italian.
They do it a lot and then
Spanish, I'm sure as well.
Yeah.
But we call it text speak because it's
very, very short and kind of abbreviated.
But it's a problem for my understanding is
because these younger generations, they use
it so much that they
really kind of start
forgetting the proper
grammar and proper spelling.
So even you will find, I saw a
report the other day, essays or
reports handed in with these
terrible writing spelling mistakes.
That's awful.
Well, I hope, hope that people
are learning grammar and
spelling, especially
non-native learners of English.
Right.
If you're doing homework
for your English class,
don't use these, but it might
be interesting to look them up.
Let us know, though.
Do you text message people?
Do you send these text messages?
Do you have SMS service in your country?
Let us know.
Our website is englishpa.com.
All right.
We'll see you guys there.
Bye.